Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- H
  - Hayes, Catriona, Mar 9, 2009; cuid34580 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Bellerose Terrace, New York, on March 9, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Hayes, Eddie, Mar 9, 2009; cuid34581 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Eddie Hayes (b. Co. Limerick, Ireland, 1966), a narcotics detective with the New York City Police Department, emigrated in 1989. After service with the U.S. Navy, he joined the NYPD in 1996. He is married to Catriona Hayes.
    Some key themes that Hayes discusses in this history are: being Irish in the navy; racial dynamics of the navy; and being Irish in the NYPD and working in Harlem.
  - Hayes, Thomas, Jun 2, 2009; cuid34582 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is 1 hour, 22 minutes, and 11 seconds long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in San Francisco, on June 2, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
    Thomas F. Hayes (b. Co. Limerick, 1925, d. San Francisco, 2010) emigrated to California in 1949 and in 1958 started his own business there, Tom Hayes Plastering. He was a founding member of the All Ireland Social Club and the United Irish Cultural Club, as well as a longtime member of the San Francisco Gaelic Athletic Association. He was appointed a Director of the Bay Area Rapid Transit by San Francisco Mayor Joseph Alioto in 1974. He is the father of the San Francisco Fire Chief Joanne Hayes- White.
  - Hearn, Anne, Mar 31, 2012; cuid34583 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Anne Hearn (b. Co. Longford, Ireland, 1943) emigrated to the United States in 1961 and began working at Verizon Communications until she retired in 1997. She is very involved in both the Longford Association and the United Irish Counties Association of New York.
  - Heffernan, Eileen Reilly, Jun 17, 2011; cuid34584 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Eileen Reilly Heffernan (b. Bronx, New York, 1962), a former member of the Peace Corps, has taught in Washington State and in the Bronx. She is the daughter of Eileen Reilly Mescall.
  - Henchy, Seamus, Apr 23, 2013; cuid34585 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Seamus Henchy (b. Ennistymon, Co. Clare, Ireland, 1954) came to the United States in 1983 and has established a niche business in New York managing museum and gallery renovations.
  - Higgins, Brigid, May 5, 2011; cuid34586 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Brigid Higgins (b. Loughrea, Co. Galway, 1935), a former Dominican nun and New York City school teacher, emigrated to America twice: at age 9 and at age 53. She lived in Ireland between 1972-88, then returned to New York where she completed her MA in Education at Manhattan College in 1992 and became a bedside educator for Memorial Sloane Kettering.
  - Hurley, Patrick, Oct 31, 2007; cuid34587 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Patrick Hurley (b. Wellington, New Zeland, 1962), raised in County Cork, was a member of the New Irish generation who found himself in New York City in the 1980s as an "illegal" alien with few options to succeed in America without proper documentation. Along with a core group of partners, he helped to found the Irish Immigration Reform Movement in 1987 and lobbied successfully to change immigration law in the US with the passage of the Immigration Act of 1990 HR-4300 which granted thousands of non-preference visas to immigrants considered unfairly disadvantaged by previous legislation, many of whom were Irish.
- I
  - Isacsson, Fr. Alfred, Apr 29, 2011; cuid34588 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Fr. Alread Isacsson of the Carmelite Order (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1932, d. Middletown, New York, 2011) was a High School teacher and Principal at St. Albert's Junior Seminary in Middletown, New York and at Pope John Paul II High School in Boca Raton, Florida. He was also a Parochial Vicar and Pastor at Transfiguration Church in Tarrytown, New York. Fr. Isacsson drew upon the Carmelite Archives in a number of articles, papers and books that explored the Carmelite relationship of the Irish independence movement in the early 20th century.
  - Isaly, Rosalie, Jun 9, 2011; cuid34589 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Rosalie Isaly (b. Chicago, Illinois, 1943) was born into a family in the Chicago funeral parlor business. Her father was John Louis O'Hanley who took over operations from his father. One of seven children raised on the South Side, she attended Loyola College and studied art in Perugia, Italy, and French in Paris. After working in advertising and marketing in Chicago, she moved to New York where she raised her children and worked as an art teacher.
- J
  - Johnston, Lisa, Mar 26, 2009; cuid34590 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Lisa Johnston (b. 1966), an immigration lawyer in private practice in Yonkers, NY, is the great-granddaughter of immigrants from Co. Donegal. She was an instrumental member of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement and is a board member of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 80 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on March 26, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
- K
  - Keane, Maurice, Oct 24, 2013; cuid34591 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    Maurice "Moss" Keane (b. Castleisland, Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1960) developed a successful business in property renovation in Boston for which he has received numerous awards.
  - Keating, Geoffrey, 2014; cuid34799 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_14)
    Geoffrey Keating was born in 1957 in New York, New York. He married and has two children. He is an ambassador in Ireland's Department of Foreign Affairs and, at the time of the 2014 interview, was preparing for his next posting as Ireland's Ambassador to Singapore.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Geoffrey Keating's office in Dublin, Ireland on June 20, 2014. The interview covers Keating's family, his early life, and his working life. Keating describes his parents, his father's work as an Irish diplomat, and his mother's work as a medical doctor. He recounts his early life living in various countries and his education at different schools in Ireland and England. He recounts his decision to join the Department of Foreign Affairs in 1981, his postings to Italy, Bulgaria, and the United States, and the impact of these postings on his family.
  - Kehoe, George, Jun 2, 2011; cuid34592 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    George Kehoe (b. Dallas, Texas, 1952) a 3rd generation Irish American, has worked as an actor, writer and teacher. He wrote and directed Hunger, a play based on the prison writings of 1981 Irish hunger striker Bobby Sands.
  - Kelleher, Erin, Jul 5, 2011; cuid34593 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Erin Kelleher (b. Mt. Kisco, New York, 1973), the grandchild of four immigrants from County Cork, is a pediatrician in Tuckahoe, New York. Her mother was raised in Jersey City; her father was a fifth grade teacher. A graduate of the University of Notre Dame, she studied medicine at Trinity College Dublin, where she met her Irish-born husband.
  - Kelleher, Margaret, Jul 30, 2013; cuid34594 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    Margaret Kelleher (b. Mallow, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1964) studied for a Ph.D. in English Literature at Boston College, returned to teach in Ireland in 1990, and in 2012 was appointed Chair of Anglo-Irish Literature at University College Dublin.
  - Kelleher, Orla, 2016; cuid34800 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_91)
    Orla Kelleher was born in 1970 in Kilgarvan, County Kerry, Ireland. She immigrated to the United States in 2004 and began working at the Aisling Irish Center in Yonkers, New York. In 2006 she became the Executive Director of the Center.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Orla Kelleher's office at the Aisling Irish Center in Yonkers, New York on April 21, 2016. The interview covers Kelleher's family, early life in Ireland, her immigration to the United States (US), and her working life. Kelleher describes her early life in a small village in County Kerry, Ireland; her family; and her experience entering the workforce in County Cork in 1990. She recounts her visits to the US, her decision to take an extended break from work in 2004 in the US, and her decision to remain in the US permanently. She describes the work of the Aisling Irish Center to provide support and advice to Irish immigrants and its role in the community. She also discusses her work with the Coalition of Irish Immigration Centers.
  - Kelley, Joseph, 2015; cuid34801 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_53)
    Joseph Kelley was born in 1945 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He graduated from Villanova University in Villanova, Pennsylvania with a bachelor's degree in political science in 1967. He received his law degree from Villanova University's Charles Widger School of Law in 1970. He married Donna Deverant in 1969.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at the Joseph Kelley Law Firm in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on April 17, 2015. The interview contains Joseph Kelley's family history and his father's involvement with the Philadelphia Council of the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO). He details his motivations for attending law school and his work representing labor unions in Philadelphia. He recounts the beginning of his involvement with the Commodore Barry Arts and Cultural Center in Philadelphia to rework the center's Internal Revenue Service status and his continuing presence on their Board of Directors.
  - Kelly, Catherine, Apr 24, 2013; cuid34595 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    Catherine Kelly (b. Carrickmore, Co. Tyrone, Northern Ireland, 1962) was a Morrison Visa recipient who grew up in Northern Ireland. She teaches Political Science with a focus on American and International Politics.
  - Kelly, Donald A., Nov 15, 2006; cuid34596 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Donald Kelly (b. 1935), is a retired Senior Vice President of Emigrant Savings Bank and President of the Executive Committee of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center.
  - Kelly, Marguerite, Sister, 2015; cuid34802 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_44)
    Sister Marguerite Kelly was born in 1938 in Caltra, County Galway, Ireland. She is a sister in the Missionary Franciscan Sisters of the Immaculate Conception. She worked in Italy, the United States, Bolivia, and Peru before settling permanently in the US in 2003. At the time of the 2015 interview, she was the Executive Director of the Irish Pastoral Centre in Boston.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at the Irish Pastoral Centre in Boston, Massachusetts on March 12, 2015. The interview covers Sister Marguerite Kelly's early life in Ireland, her life as a religious sister, and her working life in Boston, Massachusetts. Kelly describes her family members and her childhood on a farm in County Galway, Ireland. She discusses her education, her decision to join the Missionary Franciscan Sisters of the Immaculate Conception in 1955, and the reaction of her parents to her vocation. She recounts her early experiences of religious life, her postings in Italy and the United States (US), and her missionary work in Bolivia between the late 1960s and 1980. She discusses her education at Boston College in Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts, her experiences teaching in the Boston area in the 1980s, and her work as a missionary in Peru in the late 1980s. She discusses her return to the Boston area in 1989, her experiences between 1989 and her introduction to the Irish Pastoral Centre in 2004, and her work at the Centre between then and the time of the interview. She describes her responsibilities at the Centre, including her involvement in the senior citizen program and her work to write the Centre's by-laws.
  - Kelly, Patrick, M.D., Jan 17, 2009; cuid34597 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview took place in New York City on January 17, 2009, and the interviewers Myriam Nyhan and Marion Casey.
    Patrick J. Kelly (b. 1941), a neurosurgeon and Chairman of the Department of Neurological Surgery at NYU Langone Medical Center. Third generation Irish raised in Lackawanna, New York, he pioneered Computer-Assisted Stereotactic Neurosurgery and founded the New York-based charity the Brain Tumor Foundation.
  - Kelly, Ray, Nov 19, 2010; cuid34598 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Ray Kelly (b. Manhattan, 1941) is Commissioner of the New York City Police Department (1992-1994; 2001-present). He is a Vietnam veteran and retired Marine Colonel, with advanced degrees from St. John's University, New York University and Harvard. As a second-generation Irish American with ties to Counties Cavan, Roscommon, and Longford, Kelly served as Grand Marshal of the 2010 New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade. His brother is Don Kelly.
  - Kelly, Sr. Theresa, Nov 8, 2007; cuid34599 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Sister Theresa begins the discussion with a description of her parents lives in Ballinlough, County Roscommon, Ireland. She includes information such as what life was like there in general, as well as the work involved with owning a family farm. She recalls that her parents lived on the same street but came over to America separately and for different reasons in the early 1920s.
    Sister Theresa talks about her parents' occupations after arriving in America. Her mother worked as a housekeeper and was later promoted to cook. Her father's occupation as a police officer in combination with her mother's strong money management enabled the couple to buy their own home. This was the house that Sister grew up in the Brooklyn, New York neighborhood of Bushwick with her two older siblings, James and Mary Anne. When Sister was five, her older brother left to attend the seminary, St. Joseph's College in Princeton, New Jersey, eventually fulfilling his passion and becoming ordained as a Vincentian priest. Sister explains the differences between Vincentian and diocesan priests, and goes on to describe a typical day for a priest and his duties in general.
    Sister Theresa attended the single-sex Catholic educational institution St. John the Baptist grammar school. She went on to attend Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School in Brookyln, also a single-sex Catholic school. Sister Theresa mentions that being around religious figures her whole life played a part in motivating her to become a nun. However, after graduating in 1952, she was not yet sure of what she wanted to do, and went on to work in the accounting department at Pfizer Incorporated. After five years, in 1957, Sister Theresa chose to join the Brooklyn Sisters of Mercy. She talks about her various assignments at different schools, ranging from her first teaching assignment in Sunnyside, Queens, to a librarian at St. Patrick's on Kent Avenue in Brooklyn, as well as her work as principal at Our Lady of Refuge in East Flatbush, Brooklyn.
    It was during her assignment at St. Patrick's on Kent Avenue that Vatican II occurred. Sister Theresa describes the changes she saw in the Church, the effects the movement had on Catholic educations and the habit, as well as on the convent itself and the women within it. Sister's opinion of the reforms were mostly negative. She believes that before Vatican II the women in the convent had a strict schedule that was followed, and without that kind of structure the women felt lost; she points to this as one of the changes that provoked many women to leave. She also disliked the changes in the habit. She discusses in detail the full habit nuns used to wear before Vatican II, as well as why she enjoyed wearing it and why she still wears the modified habit today, even though it is not a requirement. However, she does mention that she enjoyed the new freedom nuns had to vacation and visit family whenever they chose, as compared to before when time away from the convent was limited. She describes her family's home in Breezy Point, Queens, and the joy it brought her to be able to go back there for vacations. Sister also discusses the effects Vatican II had on the convent, the Church and religion in general, as well as its impact on Catholic educations.
    Sister Theresa also discusses her Irish identity throughout the interview. She remembers listening to the Irish radio stations with her mother, and mentions that her sister took Irish dancing classes. She describes her Irishness as being inherent, and something that has always simply been a part of her. When asked about her Irish-American identity she explains that although she does not necessarily think about it, she knows she is Irish, and describes herself as more Irish than American, but that the greatness of America is also simply a part of who she is.
    Sister Theresa ends with a discussion about her current position at Our Lady of Mercy Academy in Syosset, New York, as event coordinator, where she organizes school events and fundraisers. She mentions the various events she handles yearly and the amount of money raised at some of them.
    This oral history with Sister Theresa Kelly was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 2 hours, 28 minutes long, on 3 CDs, and has been logged at ten minute intervals. Sister Theresa Kelly was interviewed on November 8, 2007, at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Kristina Galati, Linda Dowling Almeida, and Joseph Ready.
    Sr. Theresa Kelly (b. 1934) a member of the Sisters of Mercy of the Mid-Atlantic Community who, after a long teaching career, retired as Principal of Our Lady of Refuge in East Flatbush, Brooklyn (NY).
  - Kelly, Thomas, Dec 14, 2005; cuid34600 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    The interview is approximately 1 hour, 36 minutes long. The interview took place on December 14, 2005, and the interviewers were Tess Sheridan and Linda Dowling Almeida.
    Thomas Kelly (b. 1961), author of several books including Payback, The Rackets, and Empire Rising. Drawing on his working class background in New York City and New Jersey he writes about the Irish experience in the construction industry. Kelly put himself through school working as a sandhog digging Water Tunnel Number Three in New York, graduated from Fordham, earned a Masters degree from the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard and served as advance director for New York City Mayor David Dinkin's reelection campaign in 1993 before retiring to write full time.
  - King, Peter T., Nov 28, 2005; cuid34601 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Peter T. King (b. 1944), is a Republican Congressman from Long Island and one of the architects of the Northern Ireland peace process in the 1990s.
  - Kirwan, Larry, Oct 18, 2011; cuid34602 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    Larry Kirwan (b. 1954) is a writer and musician and is most notable as the lead singer of the Irish rock band Black 47. He also hosts the Sirius Satellite Radio show Celtic Crush.
- L
  - Landigan, Rosemary, Jan 22, 2011; cuid34603 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Rosemary Landigan (b. New York, New York, 1935), the daughter of immigrants from County Armagh who met in New York at the Armagh Ball, was born and raised in the Bronx, New York. Her father was a publican and one of the founders of the County Armagh Pipe and Drum Band. She made her first trip to Ireland in 1936 and her second trip in 1950.
  - Lang, Danny, Dec 13, 2006; cuid34604 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Lavery, Bobby, Jun 3, 2009; cuid34605 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Bobby Lavery (b. Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland, 1948), is a former political prisoner at Long Kesh and elected Sinn Fein representative for North Belfast. He emigrated with his American-born wife to San Francisco, CA, in 2000. Before its demise, he worked in Development for the New College of California.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 90 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in San Francisco, California, on June 3, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Laverty, Charles (two interviews), Oct 16, 2009-Feb 19, 2010; cuid34606 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Charles A. Laverty (b. Moy, Co. Tyrone, Ireland, 1930), is a journalist and retired reserve member of the U.S. Army Special Forces. He emigrated to New York in 1948. Active in Irish Republican circles thereafter, he served as President of the New York Irish History Roundtable from 2003–2007.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 1 hour, 14 minutes, and 41 seconds long, on 1 CD. The interview took place over two sessions in New York City, on October 16, 2009 and February 19, 2010, and the interviewer was Marion Casey.
  - Lawless, Anne, 2014; cuid34803 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_30)
    Anne Lawless was born in 1949 in Galway, County Galway, Ireland. She graduated from University College Galway in 1971. She married in 1971 and has four children. She immigrated to the United States in 1998.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Anne Lawless's home in Chicago, Illinois on November 21, 2014. The interview covers Lawless's childhood, life in Ireland, and her life in the United States (US). Lawless discusses her family, her education, and her decision to attend a boarding school. She recounts her experiences at University College Galway between 1967 and 1971, and discusses meeting her husband in 1970. She discusses the jobs her husband held, the fact that she worked in the home until her children had left home, and the fact that she enjoyed working behind the bar in their pubs in Galway. She also discusses her and her husband's decision to immigrate to the US in 1998, her children's professions, and her opinion of Galway at the time of the interview.
  - Lawless, Billy, 2014; cuid34804 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_30_ER_28)
    Billy Lawless was born in 1950 in Galway, County Galway, Ireland. He married in 1971. He immigrated to the United States in 1998.
    This interview was conducted by Íde B. O'Carroll at Billy Lawless's home in Chicago, Illinois on November 21, 2014. Lawless's wife, Anne Lawless, participates in the interview. The interview covers Lawless's early life in Ireland, his working life, and his political activity. Lawless describes his parents and grandparents, and their working lives. He recounts stories from his childhood, including distributing milk with his father in Galway. He discusses different fields in which he worked before his immigration to the United States, including farming, forestry, and hospitality. He discusses his work in immigration reform, his introduction to the topic, and his opinion on President Barack Obama's Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals policy.
  - Lawlor, Margaret (Cis), Feb 9, 2012; cuid34607 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    Margaret "Cis" Lawlor (b. Co. Offaly, Ireland, 1920) remembers her paternal grandparents sharing their memories of surviving the Famine when growing up in Co. Offaly. She emigrated to the United States for the first time in 1948 and then returned to Ireland in 1954. After coming back to the US in October 1954, she raised her family in Manhattan and in Elmhurst, Queens.
  - Lawlor, Tom, Jul 30, 2011; cuid34608 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Tom Lawlor (b. Shanahoe, Co. Laois, Ireland, 1941) was a member of the Co. Laois association of New York. He retired from the New York Police Department and moved to Ireland.
  - Leddy, Mary, Sep 5, 2013; cuid34609 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    Mary Leddy (b. Co. Cavan, Ireland, 1947) has worked in major hotels in the US and Ireland and is now theConcierge at the Harvard Club of New York.
  - Leonard, Pat, Jul 21, 2011; cuid34610 (Box 2, Folder 42)